so this is a Newton universe petite
Subhadra and the notes in itself it's
quite long it's about 25 paragraphs
he gets very technical so I think I'd
rather speak about a principle but it's
an father then people can't dwell on
reflect keep in mind and then when they
did Nana valence no to put it some pada
we can sort of give more of a context
rather than dealing with every
particular point in Univera himself
raises in in his notes because the
points are self-explanatory really the
reputation of the traditional
interpretation and so on it's all in
there but I thought maybe just to
contribute to the to the general
perspective on the principle that it's
Ambala and also practical applications
that can they can then result in freedom
from ownership then results in freedom
from suffering if you're not seeing your
with the grain of it as a certain
describe means ignorance is the cause
for your out outflow who was the world
simultaneously right there and then if
you see then you you're against the
grain of it which means the principle
still remains there but is the direction
of it that has changed so his insistence
on positional butter being the one life
interpretation it's a really an
interpretation in a sense of that they
can be different interpretation his
insistence was ultimate in a sense of
this is the the principle that cannot be
diluted or compromised so sometimes
people say oh yes so mother are the
teachers also teaching the particular
body is only it's a present principle
but when you look at it how how their
feet how their interpretation of it how
the view of it goes he comes down to
it's still the commentary of type of
outlook as in it's still taken to be an
explanation just instead of spreading it
over over three three lifetimes they get
to they concentrate it in solving this
one or in one moment but it isn't it's
not even moment
really so to speak it's a simultaneous
principle that as such it's timeless
it's a calico
and that's the principle of simultaneous
presence of two different things they
cannot be examined or taken apart
individually without the other one being
applied that's why the potato bada and
the principle of Sankara is basically
the same thing so so we should probably
address but I think that there has to be
a separate video the whole phenomenon of
Sankara determination because most most
people's ideas about determination and
determinations in petit Sampada are on
the lines of a cause and effect which is
exactly what what the traditional
reputation is that this is a cause this
result and this is the return another
cause and then another result and so on
and so and and because of that if it's a
cause and effect it must involve time
and as such it cannot be that that
fundamental principle they can making
sort of will make understand the nature
of action the nature of ownership and
the nature of the nature of craving and
the nature of imminent that takes you
with that grain so whenever there is a
there is a an involvement of time in the
explanation or the principle means it is
not as fundamental as but its own father
is because with this this is that's how
every petition ibadah formulation
because there are few different ones
that there was very in the suitors but
always it will start with whenever with
this this is the presence of this this
is present there various translations of
this as well but the point is with both
sides of that statement are in the
present tense it's not open this has
arised having arise ceased then this is
the result that came after it which is
usually how people take what it somebody
to be it says with this this is or with
this this comes to be or with this there
is a being of this two things
simultaneously present on two different
levels that's why it's also so hard to see
that's why it's also so hard to see
because it's not something you can just
observe because it already includes your
observation nature your generation is
already implied in it's like nominal
vineya vineya nama Rupa you look at one
it's implied by the other so so the
whole point the whole point of this of
the sermon of this principle is because
it automatically disables you basically
from any sense of ownership because you
realize there is no place for a sense of
self in the two equally simultaneously
mutually determined things if you look
at one is eternal but the other if you
look at their lives if anybody other one
obviously you can't even like the word
I'm describing you can't even look it
like that you can't look at the one and
then look at the other because they will
require you to step outside of your
experience and that's that's not
possible so the actual the actual principle of
so the actual the actual principle of
two simultaneous things you are within
those things your experience as a whole
is within those things so you can't see
them on equal footing you can only see
one and then discern that it's
determined by the other and that
discernment is a valid thing if you know
how to do it if you know where to look
for it but if you expect to see the two
simultaneous things pressure together to
the equal extent in front of you means
you the third thing which means these
are not two fundamental things upon
which your whole experience rests so the
whole the whole the whole principle of
that that Sawada can be summed into
whenever with it with with this this is
and and even the the scholars who kind
of endorse the traditional
interpretation even they could not
negate the fact that this is the the
basic statement very fundamental
statement for every petition bada always
implies present present so that's where
some of the more renowned once tried to
reconcile this more discrepancy of the
Buddha statement apetito by the
rationalist this arises with the
traditional view
we're by having something else arisen
this is the result of it so they try to
reconcile it basically by dismissing it
by dismissing this is this most
condensed formulation so all look in the
in the they would they would say things
like like that a statement that with
this this is is just an abstract
principle of petites on pod but that's a
that's quite a quite a poor attempt I
suppose at the at a circumventing the
problem because no matter how abstract
the principle might be for you if it's a
principle means that what is to follow
as a description of a principle cannot
be done metrically opposed to that
principle which is again a belief that
many of them famous scholars with hair
oh this is a principle that states with
the rising of this this is but then the
actual explanation of principle
completely ignores the very principle of
simultaneous presence and then carries
on he explained you to you a three life
interpretation of how this leads to that
and then this leads to that and so on so
even if we take it to be an abstract
principle as such everything else that
follows encounter it must be included
principle otherwise it's not a principle
but the fact that those scholars
themselves call it a principle means
they understand the importance of it and
because that principle remains the same
that's why but teaching by the
formulation found in the sutras was was
not always comprised of 12 factors the
numerous occasions were was it Sally
Athena was omitted and they were an
avocation where he doesn't even go into
the whole dependence of evil
determination of Sankara to vijnana and
NVIDIA to Sankara but it just comes to
nama Rupa determined by banana and
bananas determined by no Rupa and that's
it or another ones in a vegan acharya
where where it stops after there was
after feeling and craving and then
taking up the rods and fights and
quarreling and so on so you realize
human action is based on the principle
of ignorance and that's exactly what is
known about expenditure and human action
is always present like whatever that's
why your intentions determine your that
your present intention to determine your
actions and that's where you're fully
bound by it and being those intentions
always being present means there is
always present ignorance in regard to
those actions so you remove the
imminence means your extras are not
determined by it anymore which means
your actions are then free from sense of
self conceit ownership and so on means
there is no action of you to join there
is no action they will perpetuate they
will maintain your your persistence in
the domain of samsara and the whole idea
of of the free that the rebirth and so
again it's based on the external
projection external view of yourself
well but there is this public world
between habit and then for as long as
I'm being around I will be traveling
from this life to another after another
life to another life but but those
people fail to see there is no such
public world that can be known
independently from your experience right
here right now in other words when you
think about a public world you're
thinking it privately in your within
your experience as a whole and you're
fooling close within that and that's
again that's what means whatever you do
stays with you
so the idea rebirth being like this
traveling through this public world that
we all inhabit it's completely mistaken
the idea of rebirth is closer to the
persistence of your point of view that
you have right here right now now I'm
not saying about persistence of yourself
awareness that's that's a different
thing but the point of view the
direction of your view that's what stays
and that's what oh that's why you can
remember previous lives because it's
through this point of view same as you
remember yesterday same as you remember
ten days ago ten years ago if you
develop your mind some people have the
ability to remember ten lifetimes ago
now because they transcended this this
five aggregates which is impossible you
still stay within it but you your view
of it reaches further back but the only
reason can reach further back is it's
because all it's within the same
of the file of this experience as a
whole and with a sudden himself he for
one person remembers one life my life
times five hundred lifetimes all they do
remember is these five aggregates or one
among them so the whole idea of of this
rebirth being this traveling through
this mysterious universe and the
traditions are explained it is
completely based on this fallacy of the
external world that you can experience
subjectively independent of your point
of view right here right now so in that
that's also another way Yale doesn't
necessarily talk about that but that's
that's another tagging as to why
regarding that it's about as an
explanation is wrong because there's
really nothing to explain
he's either the point of view that you
go with the grain with ignorance with
the craving with lust and desire or the
point of view that has been purified and
and uprooted any and he uprooted from
any greed aversion or delusion
two practical terms the the principle of
petites and father
it's not about understanding the
connections between the 12 factors or 16
factors or 8 factors it's about seeing
the principle for yourself right here
right now and that principle is with
this this is which is exactly the the
the the what sotapanna sees when he
becomes a soda burner which is whatever
has the nature arising has the nature to
cease because of that simply because of
that because it has a reason
that's why equal cease so he doesn't
need to see the cessation in order to
know in impermanence on the contrary the
impermanence the cessation is implied in
the presence of thing present on its own
he has a reason whatever has the nature
of arising because of that nature it
will have to cease but usually people
expect I must see the destruction
disappearance of this thing oh yes
that's impermanent see how everything
got destroyed they failed to see that
seeing the destruction has a reason for
you so that's a manifestation and the
impermanence that the Buddha talks about
is on the level of that presently
enduring manifestation whatever that
manifestation might be whether it's a
manifestation of something being created
or a manifestation in your experience of
something being destroyed
either way manifestation is there
because it's manifested that's why it's
impermanent because it's manifested on
its own that's why I can't own it and
that's exactly what petition will bother
principle is seeing that the
independence of the origin phenomenon
independence from your point of view
upon which your point of view must rest
like if this thing has an arisen on its
own you would not simply well you will
not exist you will not even be able to
conceive it as mine let alone let alone
procreate it further and act out of it
so practically you want to see the
simultaneous presence the two things
they determine your experience as a
whole there is nothing outside of it
because when you think outside that's
your internal experience so you can't
step outside of your five aggregates and
there is no need to all you need to do
is it to cease to see that five
aggregates are
fully operating fully self-sufficient as
they are without any need of ownership
or the master agent that controlled it
furthermore once you start seeing it you
realize it's impossible to own them and
it's impossible to controlling because
that we require you to step outside of
it and take possession of it take the
direction of it and it's not incidental
that our tallada the self view one of
the first fetters that firstly fetters
that sort upon abandons it's not
incidental that adovada
is it is that assumption of the extra
temporal changes the self self that's
independent of your experience as a
whole like all feeling perception all of
this but myself is this ultimate entity
that's beyond that but if you start to
see that your sense of self which is
real as such it's not an illusion it's
real as a mistake mistakes are real
they're mistaken in its content but it's
been phenomenal aaja CLE and arising of
mistake is manifested and that mistake
is human resistance the mistake is is is
based on ignorance and you know there's
a mistake if there is lost in your
experience you will know there is an
essential mistake if there is a will in
your experience you will know there is
an extension mistake if there is
delusion appropriation concede sensor
self in your experience so these are the
symptoms of that exist tential
discrepancy that you maintain that
mistake so first you need to acknowledge
it because it's just say oh it's not
real I think the other is no self
there's nothing real there you're
dismissing the entire mistake and you're
certainly not gonna understand the
principle of simultaneous dependence so
seeing it as a mistake as a real
persisting mistake is the first step so
I have a sense of self that I cannot
deny that's not issue denying it is the
issue so you don't deny it now look at
it can they tend to self be there
continue existing may persist in its
manifestation without this random living
operating body beating heart breathing
lungs without this world being
persisting there being unaffected with
all the a great elements allowing it can
can can I remain even for
longer if something comes and just wipes
away my entire boat it is gone this
integrates it's inconceivable so it's
not about the nonsense itself it's about
putting it in the right place and the
right place is second to the experience
as a whole that is first second to the
body second to the foam feeling
perception intentions and second to the
consciousness will imagine so you read
so you don't want to be denying it you
want to change the order or as the as
the suitors will say when somebody would
understand what ability general oh it's
like lecture like correcting the order
putting first at which was second and
that's the whole point you want to you
want to reset the order properly because
that's the only way you can approve that
sense of self denying it still affirms
it indulging it affirms it ignoring it
maintains it maintains it's already
existing affirmation so what you can do
though is see dependent on that which
cannot be your sense of self which is
like your body for example your
functioning heart functioning brain
you've no saying those functions yet
your whole life depends upon it
so it's because people don't think about
these things
sufficiently enough that's how you get
to ignore the mistake or phone and ship
and so on if you start think about it
then you're gonna then you'll you will
realize that even the most personal
sense of self is still directly
dependent upon the basis of this life
for which you have no saying so then all
you can truly say up with your rising
with with the persistence of this this
persists with this this is without this
this cannot be there is no room for me
in between or outside or left-to-right
from it there never was not knowing that
never was room in there for you that's
how you place yourself in it another
quick practical take on it usually
people think I am because of that things
are mine start reversing that that their
view and and start regarding it as know
it because I keep taking things as mine
mine that's why I am but once you when
you have been taking things as yours for
so long that's how that sense of I am
start taking priority and then taking things
taking priority and then taking things
is mine which is really the cause the
the the fuel for the sense of I am
becomes second and is seen as a result
of because of I am but you again if you
deny I am then you deny the whole
problem so there is sense itself and you
don't deny it you want to regard it as
not belonging to me so my own sense of
self is not actually mine
why is not mine because it depends upon
its fully determined it's it's it's its
manifestation possessed on account of
things that I cannot own at the same
time so my sense of self depends upon
that which cannot be mine thus how can
that sense yourself belong to me because
if you truly mind its origins its
control would be within my power but it
isn't so I can say this is my this obeys
to me until it's taking away which means
it was never really yours that's why the
Buddha compared the whole existence that
the sense existence everything to the
like borrowed borrowed jewelry borrow go
sensuality and so on you borrow it and
if you have something borrowed you're
using it as if it's yours that's not
necessarily a problem the problem is
when you forget that you borrowed it and
that's exactly what ignorant system
because it's too unpleasant to keep
maintaining the perspective that this is
not mine my feelings are not mine thinks
that the dearest to me are only borrowed
I'm nothing basically that's quite
frightening if the mind hasn't been used
to thinking about it so the first
protocol is ignore it that's the easiest
with the grain solution is just I'll
ignore the fact that this is Bordeaux
that this will be theory could be taken
away and I cannot own it and because of
that because this because of that
ignorance this whole mass of suffering
arises and that's why I don't who stops
ignoring that who can never ignore it
again still speaks talk uses eats walks
and so on but he doesn't he cannot
mistake any of that for any ownership he
cannot conceive it as this hood to say
as mine as belonging to me as
I am so it's it's important to maintain
these perspectives because it's simply
through not dwelling on them that's how
you that's how you that's how you
perpetuate the existential mistake I'm
talking about by ignoring it you are
you're fueling it so it's not incidental
that thinking about it is very
unpleasant that's how murder makes sure the nobody
that's how murder makes sure the nobody
thinks about it voluntarily takes
determination effort in repetitive sort
of strength and training because it's
it's it's completely against the whole
nature of experience to know think about
it and to go with what's offer to you so
I am because or rather the sense of me
sense of sense of I am I am my own
because I take things to be mine
simultaneous presence of the assumed
ownership is why there is a sense of I I
am without that basis being there
persisting there cannot be a sense of I
am possessed it so how do you remove the
basis that is necessary for your sense
of self well you can't remove it as in
to prevent it from arising because that
would imply that your sense of self is
in control of it and has saved as to
what arises and what disappears but you
can stop regarding it as yours how you
stop regarding it is yours well by stop
gratuitously delighting in welcoming essential sense
delighting in welcoming essential sense
pleasures by stop notoriously trying to
get rid of the unpleasant feelings its
desired and lost in regard to feelings
that's how you maintain the ownership
unquestioned desire unquestioned lost
the ownership gets maintained
unquestioned ownership sense of self is
fully established having a grip over you
so my sense of self does not belong to
me it's there as in a reason persisting
phenomena but I cannot own it
even if I want to another way to think
about it is understand the nature of
ownership just take take a phenomenon of
ownership belonging what is it what what
does it what is it what is it determined
by if you say this is mine what does
that really mean to you does it mean you
have a you have a say in it does it mean
you're truly the owner and you realize
if you start think about it as well it's
it's at most sense of ownership is is on
the sense of it's on the level of
entitlement it cannot be more than that
you just cannot be more than that even
if you made something you created
yourself from scratch the fact that all
those scratches that you had from which
you were able to create these things
they were given to you beforehand which
means there doesn't matter how far you
exercise your creation your sense of
self your ownership your control it's
always going to be secondary to that
persistent basis of things having a
reason beforehand on their own and
you're not saying that that's what the
Buddha would encourage to think about
the four Great elements which is things
there isn't on their own and you have no
saying that and when those four Great
elements change nothing that has been
depending upon them can remain standing
unaffected so sense of ownership you can
reflect on that what is it's it's
necessary presently enduring basis
any sense of ownership object people
doesn't matter
hmm any sense of ownership
keep something is mine
if something is truly mine letting in
you don't don't rush answering it or
defining it just what does it mean to
have things belong to me
what does it mean being mine and you
realize that as I said it's in the level
of entitlement but then you can also see
that be mine means being pleasant means
having implying the prospect of pleasure
would you gladly regard something as
mine if that thing is threatening to you
would you be happy about having cancer
or a disease or something that can kill
you know you'd want to get rid of it I
don't want this to be mine so there is a
common thread to everything that's
regarded as mine which is pleasure and
that's why it's not incidental and
anybody talks about it that pleasure is
the sense of mastery over things it's
inherently bound to pleasure because if
there is no pleasure you would not want
it and you would certainly not been
dodging the ideas of control and and mmm
and mastery over such things so sense of
mine is a sense of entitlement that is
bound with a weight with a sense of
pleasure which means then sense of mine
is basically sense of entitlement
towards pleasure you feel like you have
right to experience pleasure and see to
that just to that extent only the the
view has only already transgressed into
the domain that doesn't belong to the
domain of the of the aggregate of
feelings you have no right to choose
what you want to work what you want to
feel or not but yet you feel entitled
why is that where is that entitlement
rooted in oh it's rooted in me ignoring
the fact that I have no right to choose
what I feel so simply through ignoring
what's right in front of you you develop
the sense of entitlement which is the
sense of ownership which is the sense of
myself the master their ego everything
else the whole suffering and the mess
that comes from it
comes from you ignoring the simple
truths that are right in front of the
universal truths with the presence of
this this is present so with the
presence of all these with the presence
of feelings for example my craving is
there can I crave for pleasure the
feeling is not there in the first place
no can I crave for pleasure when the
feeling has disappeared No so it's the
persistence of the reason pleasure
that's necessary simultaneous basis for
my craving of that pleasure two words or
against from it and that's but it's in
part in the nutshell so can I then not
create in the presence of pleasure yes
and that's exactly the path it's invalid
it goes against the grain so externally
so to speak on the surface surface
nothing has changed there is pleasure
pleasure remains the aggregates remain
but what has changed is the attitude of
craving towards or against and so on the
attitude of craving has disappeared so
now there is no craving on the basis of
pleasure and the pleasure still arises
and the paint's terrorises and the
neutral feeling still arises but the
direction of their was based on ignoring
the the nature of these things that
arise on their own the five aggregates
that direction is gone because you
stopped ignoring it that's really
nourishing anyway it's quite a good good
translation for a region because of EJ
is not it's not a metaphysical secret in
all mmm a lack of sort of information
that that you need to discover to some
mystical practice they will be revealed
to you some truths that are hidden it's
actually your very attitude towards your
own feelings your own perceptions your
own intention the attitude of ignoring
the fact that you can't own it even if
you want to and you want you but you
realize that you want to only because
you think you can on it but you can't
and if you stop ignoring that and again
if you can't do that overnight you
because ignoring has been dance for eons
Indians Indians Indians you've been done
for so long
it's your starting point it's the stuff
that will amend a visa has no
discernible beginning before which the
mind wasn't ignorant and then it's
ignorant but a beach
cigarettes shouldn't be there because
it's incompatible with the way things
are that's why our on trip is irreversible
that's why our on trip is irreversible
once you fully realize that Abby just
shouldn't be there
it cannot be there it ceases to be there
and that's why the Buddha said oh that's
that's when when his mind realized the
mind was always pure and bright the
aggregates were always on unpolluted by
by a vision by craving because it cannot
be in the aggregate it's not
understanding their grades that's why I
was there once you understood that's why
I can never be there ever again
irreversible parting bond